icscr lombard reported muted earnings in
the third quarter of fy 22. the insurer
faced multiple challenges in the quarter
gone by the claims ratio continued to
rise in the health segment motor
insurance which is its largest segment
witnessed continued headwinds due to
increased competitive intensity chip
shortages in the four-wheeler segment at
weak festive demand in the two-wheeler
segment added to that there's been no
revision in the prevailing third-party
motor tariff rates for more than two
consecutive years now meanwhile merger
vinbharti axa got reflected in the
current fiscal and further weighed on
the company's financial performance
despite these issues the non-life
insurer did manage to post a profit as
the underwriting loss in q3f by 22 was
offset by higher investment income icici
lombard's gross direct premium income
the gdpi stood at 13 311 crores in the
first nine months of fy 22 a growth of
27 on a year-on-year basis given its
merger with bhartiyaksa general
insurance the numbers represent that of
the merged entity effective from the
quarter ending june 2021. as a result
the first nine months of fy 22 numbers
are not comparable with that of the
previous year premium growth was weak
adjusted for the merger however icsc
lombard's gdpi growth of 27 in the first
nine months of fi 22 looks good if we
compare it to that of the industry which
reported a double-digit growth of 11.2
on a lower base for the similar period
this implies that the deal with bharti
aksar has helped icaci lombard
consolidate its market position
the acquisition has aided icici
lombard's growth in the current times
when organic growth has slowed due to
various reasons motor insurance which i
said was the largest segment for the
insurers saw a muted growth due to
overall weak demand sentiment in vehicle
sales health insurance growth was robust
last year given enhanced awareness due
to the pandemic and an attitude shift of
customers towards protection buying so
in q3 growth and retail health moderated
due to base effect low business from
icici bank in the retail health segment
added to the headwinds icici lombard
increased premium for group health
policies on an average by about 15 to 20
in the previous quarter following the
surge in claims and its adverse impact
on loss ratio in spite of the increase
it has been able to retain over 90 of
corporate customer accounts the
underlying environment suggests that
customers are now willing to pay a
higher premium for better coverage thus
creating an opportunity for icici
lombard to grow in this segment
commercial segments meanwhile like
property and casualty saw healthy growth
in sync with the current economic
climate icici lombard's combined ratio
which is a measure of an insurance
company's profitability increased to 111
percent in the first nine months of f by
22 compared to 99 during the same period
last year leading to underwriting loss
the combined ratio of below 100
indicates that the insurer is receiving
more money from premiums than paying out
in claims and operating expenses now the
combined ratio if you look at it is the
sum of loss or claims ratio and the
expense ratio the expense ratio if you
look at it inched by 330 basis points
year on year mainly due to the merger
since bharti axa operated at a higher
expense ratio there is scope to improve
operating efficiency by reducing
overheads like branch cost branding and
even marketing costs for that matter
deterioration and loss ratio was largely
driven by higher claims in the health
business there has been increased
frequency in non-covet health claims
meanwhile also health inflation has been
higher as seen in the 9 to 10 percent
increase in average claim size
investment income more than compensated
for underwriting loss leading to small
profit in the nine months of fy 22. at
the current market price icici lombard
is trading at a pricey valuation of 7.6
times trailing book value of nine months
of fy22 however the premium valuation
will sustain given its market leading
share in a secular growth sector fairly
diversified product mix multi-channel
distribution network solid technological
prowess and strong solvency profile and
healthy profitability the stock has
corrected 18 from its 52-week highs it
came under pressure as business got
impacted by higher claims and slower
growth however the company sees growth
in the motor segment to improve going
forward and expects a price hike from
the regulator also there can be
operating synergies and cost savings
from the merger which may reflect from
the second half of fy 23. now following
bharti yaksa deal parent icici bank
stake has come down from more than 51
percent to 48 this has implications as
icici bank will eventually have to bring
the stake down to 30
in september 2020 if you remember the
government gave icici bank three years
to comply with this regulation the
supply overhang could also weigh on the
stock price in the meantime
current weakness in the stock price due
to various reasons should be used
therefore as an opportunity by long-term
investors to add the stock to their
portfolio
[Music]